<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A full and true account of the life: and also the manner and method of carrying on the delusions, blasphemies, and notorious cheats of Susan Fowls. As the same was contrived, plotted, invented, and managed by wicked popish priests and other papists, with a design to scandalize our church and ministers, by insinuating that the virtue of casting forth devils, and easing persons possess'd was only in the power of their church. As also, of her tryal and sentence at the Old Baily, the 7th of this instant May, for blaspheming Jesus Christ, and cursing the Lord's prayer.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09167</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 124064188</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2292A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R177218</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">124064188</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocn 124064188</idno>
            <idno type="VID">192270</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09167)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 192270)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; 1641-1700 ; 2910:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A full and true account of the life: and also the manner and method of carrying on the delusions, blasphemies, and notorious cheats of Susan Fowls. As the same was contrived, plotted, invented, and managed by wicked popish priests and other papists, with a design to scandalize our church and ministers, by insinuating that the virtue of casting forth devils, and easing persons possess'd was only in the power of their church. As also, of her tryal and sentence at the Old Baily, the 7th of this instant May, for blaspheming Jesus Christ, and cursing the Lord's prayer.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Read in Fleet street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fowles, Susannah --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Blasphemy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:192270:1"/>
            <p>A Full and True ACCOUNT Both of the <hi>LIFE:</hi> And alſo the Manner and Method of carrying on the <hi>Deluſions, Blaſphemies,</hi> and <hi>Notorious Cheats</hi> of <hi>Suſan Fowls.</hi> As the ſame was <hi>Contrived, Plotted, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented,</hi> and <hi>Managed</hi> by wicked <hi>Popiſh Prieſts</hi> and other <hi>Papiſts,</hi> with a <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign</hi> to <hi>ſcandalize</hi> our <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,</hi> by inſinuating that the <hi>Virtue of Caſting forth Devils,</hi> and <hi>Eaſing Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Poſſeſs'd</hi> was only in the <hi>Power</hi> of their <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As alſo, Of her TRYAL and <hi>Sentence</hi> at the <hi>Old<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Baily,</hi> the <hi>7th</hi> of this inſtant <hi>May,</hi> for <hi>Blaſpheming</hi> JESUS CHRIST, and <hi>Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> the LORD's PRAYER.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>J. Read</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> 1608.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:192270:2"/>
            <head>A full and True Account of the Firſt Begining, and the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and method of Carrying on the Deluſions, Blaphemies, and notorious Cheats of <hi>Suſannah Fowles,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THo' by a wonderful Providence,</hi> God <hi>in his infinite Kindneſs to this our Nation has freed us from the Yoke and Tyranny of Popery, yet ſuch are the reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs endeavours of the buſy Agents and Incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daries of</hi> Rome, <hi>that they ſtill privately lurk about like Wolves in Sheeps Cloathing, ſeeking whom they may devour, of theſe it was of whom the Apoſtle ſays,</hi> they creep into Houſes, and lead captive ſilly women laden with Sins, <hi>&amp;c. The deſigns of the Jeſuits are to bring a Scandal upon our Church and Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that ſo by diſgracing and leſſening them they may the more commodiouſly extol and mag<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifie themſelves, as evidently appears by their wicked tampering with one</hi> Suſannah Fowls
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:192270:2"/> 
               <hi>a poor ignorant Woman, Wife to an honeſt Labourer in</hi> Hammerſmith, <hi>whom they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, for filthy Gain, to counterfeit her ſelf Poſſeſt; that ſo it might happen when the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of our Proteſtant Divines fail'd, they of the Popiſh Communion, might ſeem to have the virtue, power, and efficacy to Cast out Devils: But to be methodical.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One <hi>Jordan</hi> a Papiſt, ſeems to be the principal Promoter of this Blaſphemous Deluſion, which, for ſome time paſt, has made a great Rumour both in Town and Country. The pretences of this <hi>Fowle's</hi> Accomplices were, That upon ſome Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content ſhe had wiſhed ſeveral unlawful Wiſhes, ſuch as, <hi>That the Devil might fetch her.</hi> Curſed her ſelf, <hi>if ſhe would live ſuch a Life,</hi> &amp;c. And ſhe upon being viſited ſaid, She ſaw an Apparition in the ſhape of a Man, and afterwards ſeem'd to be P<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſeſs'd with a Devil, and had ſeeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dreadful Fits, indeed very artificially counterſeited; and made a great noi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e at Prayers, ſometimes ſhe ſaid the Devil ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd in one ſhape, and then in <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther, and at the end of her Fits would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly make two or three diſmal Squeeks
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:192270:3"/> and ſay, <hi>Now he is gone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, to ſuch a hight was her Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my grown, that on the <hi>1s.</hi> of <hi>January</hi> laſt, upon one of the Viſiters repeating the Words <hi>Lord ſave us,</hi> ſhe ſaid, <hi>I'll ſave you;</hi> and frequently upon reading the Lords Prayer, to her, ſhe ſaid, <hi>Curſe it, Dami it, Sink it;</hi> and upon repeating the Words, <hi>I believe in God the Father Allmigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> ſhe ſaid, that's me; and at repeating the Words, <hi>And in Jeſus Chriſt his only Son,</hi> ſhe ſaid <hi>that's my Son.</hi> At another time when the Words <hi>Lord ſave us,</hi> were again repeated to her, ſhe ſaid, <hi>I'll ſave you, I came to ſave you all, for which I ſhed my Blood.</hi> And always at the Naming of <hi>Jeſus</hi> ſhe would ſay, <hi>Curſe him, Curſe him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet for all this our Proteſtant Divines were too knowing to be impos'd on by ſuch feigned deluſions, they firſt obſerv'd ſhe never chang'd her Countenance dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the time of her Fits, which together with divers Methods which were us'd to make her believe they were at Prayers, when they were not, increaſed the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief ſhe was a Cheat.</p>
            <p>She ſaid, that ſhe had a Needle and P<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>per in writing given her by the Devil;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:192270:3"/> and that ſhe had a Spell given her to put about her Neck by one <hi>Jordan</hi> a Papiſt, ſome of which Profeſſion ſhe ſaid had ſent to her ſeveral times, and told her ſhe would never be cured till the Men with hair Coats and bare Legs came from the <hi>Portugal</hi> Embaſſador's: Which ſome of the Miniſters, who were Viſiters and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence againſt the Priſoner, declared, encreaſed their belief that it was a trick of the Papiſts to obtain the Credit of hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done that which Proteſtants could not, <hi>viz.</hi> to caſt out the Devil. It was alſo obſerv'd that at repeating the Lords Prayer in Latin, ſhe did not fall into her Fits as uſual when 'twas ſaid in Engliſh, which was a further Confirmation of the Cheat,</p>
            <p>To prove which more fully, one of her Viſiters heated an Iron; and when the Miniſter was at Prayer, and ſhe in her Fits as uſual, even when ſhe pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be inſenſible, he put it to her Hand, which ſhe drew away from it as ſoon as it touch'd her; and filling a Pipe of To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco, he blew the Smoke of it into her Face, which was like to have ſtifled her: And afterwards diſguiſing himſelf in an
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:192270:4"/> ugly dreſs, entered the Room where ſhe was alone; upon which ſhe immediately run out, ſaying it was the Devil, and was much frightned; which was a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther demonſtration ſhe was a Cheat. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which the Evidence threatning to knock her on the head if ſhe would not confeſs the Cheat, ſhe did it freely, and ſaid 'twas purely to get money, which ſhe alſo own'd to ſome others of the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</p>
            <p>After all this, being had before a Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, her Mittimus was made, and ſhe ſent to <hi>Newgate:</hi> and on <hi>Saturday</hi> the <hi>7th</hi> of <hi>May</hi> 1698. ſhe was Indicted at the Seſſions Houſe in the <hi>Old-Baily,</hi> for utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Blaſphemous Words againſt <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and Curſing and Damning the Lords Prayer.</p>
            <p>The priſoner in her Defence ſaid, that great Troubles had occaſioned her to fall into a diſt<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>acted condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that ſhe knew not what ſhe did; that ſhe did verily believe ſhe was either troubled with a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:192270:4"/> or bewitchd; that <hi>Jordan</hi> the papiſt had given her things both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly and outwardly; and that what ſhe had confeſt, was only to avoid being carried to priſon. But all this being look'd upon as frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and evaſion, and the Evidence being very full and clear, the Jury brought her in Guilty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>She was ſentenc'd by the Court to pay a Fine of 100 Marks, and to lie in Priſon till it be paid; to ſtand three times on the Pillory, <hi>viz.</hi> at the <hi>May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pole</hi> in the <hi>Strand,</hi> at <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringcroſs,</hi> and at <hi>Hammer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith;</hi> and ſo to find Surety for her good Behaviour fro a Twelve-month.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:192270:5"/>
            <p>As to what remains further to be ſpoken, tho' the fore-mention'd Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count will make the greateſt part in Hiſtory, He<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ents were good ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and honeſt Livers, but too neg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligent of ſeaſoning her tender years with the ſound principles of our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Faith, which gave her Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies too eaſy a Victory over her and I have reaſon to believe, he Marriage-ſtate was too unadvized<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ruſh'd in to, without a due con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration how it would entangl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her in the World, which was the occaſion of her making ſome hor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rid Wiſhes and Imprecations. To conclude, I heartily advize, all pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents to give their Children Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Education, and all perſons o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what ſtation ſoever, not to moc<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or prophane the Almighty, for Hi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Vengeance will certainly, ſooner o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> later ſeverely over-take them.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:192270:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
